When we think of Acts 1:8,
わたしたちは 使徒 1章8節を読む時—
we think of this challenging assignment
使徒たちに与えられた
割り当ての大きさについて考えます
that the apostles were given,
and we can only just imagine
them thinking about
使徒たちは“力”や “聖霊” が—
共にいるという約束について
考えたかもしれません
the other promise of “power”
and “holy spirit” being with them.
それなしでは “地の最も遠い所” にまで
行くことはできないからです
They certainly would need that to go
“to the most distant part of the earth.”
When we think back
to the first century,
1世紀当時のパウロ バルナバ テモテ
その他多くの人々は—
we think of ones such as
the apostle Paul, Barnabas, Timothy,
文字通り 可能な限り遠くの区域に
達するよう懸命に働きました
and many others
who literally tried to go
as far as they could
to reach various territories.
If we take our Bibles
and turn to the book
聖書を開いて—
ローマ 15章23, 24節を
ご覧ください
of Romans 15:23, 24,
we see summarized here
遠くの区域に達することに関する
パウロの見方がこうあります
the apostle Paul’s viewpoint
with regard to this.
Romans 15:23:
“しかし今はもう—”
“この地方に[手のつけられていない]区域は
ありませんし—”
“But now I no longer have
untouched territory in these regions,
“スペインに赴く際には
あなた方のもとに行きたいと—”
and for many years
I have longed to come to you.”
“幾年も切望してきましたので—”
And that’s the brothers in Rome.
“そこへの旅の途中でともかく—”
“Therefore, when I journey to Spain,
I hope that I will see you.”
“あなた方に一目会い［たい］”
とあります
So Paul was very concerned
about going to untouched territories.
ですから パウロは—
手のつけられていない区域に
強い関心がありました
Well, in recent times,
we can say the same
is true of Jehovah’s people,
近年のエホバの民も
同様の関心を抱いてきました
whether it be the Gilead missionaries
who have been sent out
宣教者がギレアデ学校から—
or other missionaries even prior
また その学校が設立される以前からも
送り出されてきましたし—
to the time of Gilead
being established.
多くの兄弟たちが 必要の大きな他の国に
住まいを移して奉仕しています
Or we think of the brothers
who have moved to other countries
to serve where the need is greater
or perhaps those who
have gone out to unassigned territories
どの会衆にも
割り当てられていない区域や—
or helped in areas
where very few people
ほとんどの人が証言を受けていない
地域に出向いて—
奉仕する兄弟たちもいます
get the opportunity
to hear the message.
When we hear
those experiences,
このような兄弟たちの働きは—
we certainly are encouraged
by them, aren’t we?
確かに わたしたちの大きな励みです
But perhaps we
could think this morning
しかし今日は 過去の歴史の一つの面に
目を向けてみましょう
about just one of the aspects
of the history in the past.
It’s something referred to
in the March 2016 Watchtower,
「ものみの塔」2016年3月号の
「読者からの質問」には—
in the “Questions From Readers.”
You remember this was discussing
乾いた骨の谷について述べた—
the valley of dry bones
in Ezekiel 37.
エゼキエル37章が
取り上げられています
It spoke about
the gradual restoration
その記事は 真の崇拝が
徐々に回復されることと—
of true worship,
and it made the comment
there that in the Scriptures,
聖句にある “かたかたという” 音に
関する注解があります
it speaks of a “rattling” noise.
And The Watchtower
made this comment,
it said that even
prior to the time of the end,
その記事は
終わりの時の始まる前でさえ—
there were some
faithful individuals
忠実な人々が
真の崇拝のために立ち上がり—
who stood up
in behalf of true worship.
“一般の人々の言語に聖書を翻訳しようと
した人たちもいました” と述べています
Then it said:
“Some of them endeavored to produce Bibles
in the languages of the common people.”
So let’s just think
for a few moments about some of those
これから そのような人たちについて
考えてみましょう
—perhaps less than 100 years
ラッセル兄弟が
「ものみの塔」誌の発行を始める—
before the time that Brother Russell
started The Watchtower—
100年ほど前になります
and how many
of those were motivated
彼らの多くが どれほど強く促されて
遠い所にまで赴き—
to go to distant parts
of the earth
聖書を翻訳し 現地の人々を助けたかを
考えてみましょう
to translate the Bible
and help others there.
For example,
in the year 1793,
例えば 1793年のことです
a man by the name
of William Carey
ウィリアム・ケアリー
という名の男性は—
was a British shoemaker.
英国の 靴職人でしたが—
And this shoemaker
was very impressed with the words
この人はマタイ 28章19, 20節
の言葉にとても感動し—
recorded at Matthew 28:19, 20.
すべてのクリスチャンはこの命令に
従うべきだと強く感じました
He felt strongly that all Christians
should follow that command.
So his goal was to go to India.
そして インドに行くことにします
And he arrived in India
and faced all sorts of problems
到着してから
あらゆる問題に直面しました
—eventually his wife died,
his son died as well,
妻を そして息子を失い—
インド藍栽培の職に
就かなければなりませんでした
he had to take
a job planting indigo.
But this man, within 21 years,
with the help of some others,
しかし 彼とその仲間たちは
21年ほどで—
was able to translate the Bible,
well, parts of it,
聖書全巻あるいはその一部を
36の言語に翻訳しました
in 36 languages.
Then in 1797,
別の例として 1797年—
another man,
Henry Nott,
英国出身で れんが職人の
ヘンリー・ノットがいます
from England
was a bricklayer.
And he and quite a number
of others arrived in Tahiti.
彼は 他の多くの人と共に
タヒチに到着しました
Now, four of those on that ship
彼らのうち4人は牧師でしたが—
were noted to be pastors,
正規の訓練は
何も受けていませんでした
but they had
no formal training whatsoever.
Henry Nott hadn’t had
a very good education.
ヘンリー・ノットは
れんが職人で—
基礎的な教育しか受けていませんでした
He was a bricklayer;
he just had the basic education.
But this very faithful man
しかし 忠実なこの人は
ヘブライ語とギリシャ語を学び—
decided to learn Hebrew and Greek
聖書をタヒチ語に
翻訳することにしました
and translate the Bible into Tahitian.
And he learned Tahitian very quickly,
彼は タヒチ語をすぐに覚え—
and in 1835,
after 30 years of translating,
30年後の1835年—
ついにタヒチ語への
聖書翻訳を終えました
it says that he put down his quill
and the Tahitian Bible, which,
incidentally, uses Jehovah’s name
その聖書のヘブライ語とギリシャ語
双方に—
in both the Hebrew
and the Greek sections of the Bible.
エホバのみ名が記されています
Then 1807,
Robert Morrison
1807年 ロバート・モリソンは—
—a man who was determined
to translate the Bible into Chinese.
聖書を中国語に翻訳する決意をしました
He arrived in China to find out
中国に到着して分かったことは—
that if anyone
taught a foreigner Chinese,
外国人に中国語を教える者は
死刑に処されることです
there was a death penalty.
So he remained indoors
for a couple of years
彼は 数年間 家にこもり
その間 中国語を学びます
while he learned
the Chinese language.
And then when he
started to translate the Bible,
そして 聖書の翻訳に取りかかったものの
出された皇帝の布告は—
he found out the emperor
had stated there would be a death penalty
中国でキリスト教の文書を印刷する者は
死刑に処す というものでした
for anyone who printed
Christian literature in that country.
Well, in 1819,
それでも1819年 モリソンは
中国語訳を完成させました
Morrison completed
his version there of the Bible.
In 1812,
Judson, an American,
1812年 ジャドソンと彼の妻は—
along with his wife,
left America
結婚して わずか2週間後に
米国を出発し—
just after two weeks
of marriage and,
1813年に ビルマ
現在のミャンマーに到着しました
in 1813,
arrived in Burma,
which is now known
as Myanmar.
And his determination
was to translate
彼は聖書を現地語に翻訳する決意で
いましたが—
the Bible into the local language,
which was very hard there.
困難な仕事でした
There was no dictionary;
辞書はなく
教えてくれる人は一人もいませんでした
there was no one
that could actually teach him,
and yet he set
to learning the language.
それでも 言語を学ぶことを
あきらめませんでした
He had a period of time
where he was in prison
3組の足かせをかけられ
投獄された時期もありました
with three pairs of iron fetters
attached to his body.
And he was very concerned
そんな時にも彼が心配したのは—
about his Bible manuscript
that he’d been translating,
家の床下に隠した
聖書の翻訳原稿のことでした
which was hidden
in the earth under his home.
His wife eventually brought it
to him in prison.
後に ジャドソン夫人は
それを枕に隠して—
It was hidden in a pillow.
獄中の夫に届けました
Well, this man,
by 1835,
そして 1835年 ついに彼は
現地語の聖書を完成させました
had the Bible translated
into the local language there.
But not all of these
were white missionaries
しかし 米国や英国からの
白人の宣教師ばかりではありません
from either America or England.
When the message
reached the Pacific, for example,
例えば
聖書の音信が南太平洋に届くと—
many local persons
—Polynesians—
大勢の 現地のポリネシア人が—
were very determined to go
to other islands within the Pacific
他の島々に音信を伝える強い決意を
抱くようになりました
to spread the message.
An example of this is in 1823.
例えば 1823年—
A man,
a Polynesian by the name of Papeiha,
ポリネシア人のパペイーハは—
クック諸島のラロトンガ島に音信を
伝えたいとの強い願いを抱きました
was determined to get
the message in Rarotonga,
in the Cook Islands.
So the mission ship arrived there;
宣教師の船が 島に到着し—
the two missionary couples
from overseas,
白人宣教師である
二組の夫婦が上陸します
white missionaries,
were put ashore.
There was a misunderstanding
with a drunken king,
ところが 泥酔した王との間に
誤解が生じ—
which resulted in them
being beaten up,
ひどく打ちたたかれ
持ち物はすべて盗まれ—
all their possessions
being stolen,
and them fleeing back
to the ship.
船に逃げ帰る結果になりました
But Papeiha was determined
しかし パペイーハは 是非とも—
to take the Gospel message
to those islanders.
福音をその島民に伝えたい
と思っていました
So it’s reported that he said
that he would swim ashore
記録によれば
彼は岸に向かって泳ぐと言い—
and that he called out:
“Ko Jehova toku tiaki!
“コー ジェホーバ トーク ティアーキ！”
Tei roto au i tona rima!”
“テイ ロト アウ イ トーナ リーマ！”
which translated means
と叫びました
“Jehovah is my shepherd!
これは “エホバは我が牧者—”
I am in His hand!”
“我はみ手のうちにあり！”
という意味です
And holding a book
with some translations
of the Bible in Tahitian,
タヒチ語の聖句の載った本を持ち—
he jumped overboard,
swam ashore,
海に飛び込んで 岸に向かい—
and started preaching
to the local people.
そして 伝道し始めました
Well, you can’t help
but admire that enthusiasm.
称賛に値する熱心さです
The conditions
that these missionaries met
were very, very difficult,
very primitive conditions.
これらの宣教師が直面した状況は
困難を極め—
In one country,
the missionaries lived in villages
大変野蛮なものもありました
where people
still practiced cannibalism and,
ある国の宣教師が住んでいた村では
人食いの習慣があり—
in many cases,
when the chief died,
村長が死ぬと 多くの場合
その妻たちも殺され—
all his wives were executed
at that point and buried with him.
村長と共に埋葬されます
So in the midst
of these conditions,
そのような中で 彼らは聖書を翻訳し—
these men translated
the Bible and, in many cases,
多くの場合 エホバのみ名を
聖書だけでなく—
used Jehovah’s name
not only in the Bible
個人の著作にも記しました
but in their personal writings.
What kept them going?
彼らを駆り立て—
What helped them to go
to these distant parts of the earth?
遠くの地に向かわせたのは
何だったのでしょうか？
Well, a book on the history
of the missionary work in the Pacific
南太平洋の宣教活動に関する歴史本には
次のような言葉があります
makes this interesting comment.
It says:
“Strong faith in Jehovah
“エホバに対する強い信仰は
恐れと絶望に打ち勝つ”
often overcame fear and despair.”
What an interesting thought.
実に示唆に富んだ言葉です
Well, the obvious question is,
ところで—
Were these ones anointed?
彼らは油そそがれた者なのでしょうか？
The answer obviously is,
わかりません
と答えるしかありませんね
We don’t know.
But we do know
that Jesus said in Matthew 13
わかっているのは—
マタイ13章の小麦のような
“王国の子たち” は—
there would be
wheatlike “sons of the Kingdom”
歴史を通じて
いつもいたということです
right down through history.
And if some of them
were involved with this type of work,
ですから その一部が—
I’m sure we wouldn’t be surprised.
遠い地へ宣教に行ったとしても
不思議ではありませんが—
And in the future,
we will no doubt find out
そうだったかどうかは
将来はっきりするでしょう
if they were involved
with that work or not.
But what about us today?
わたしたちは何をすべきでしょうか？
Well, does it mean we
have to all leave our Bethel homes now
もちろん 今すぐにベテルを出て
遠い地に行こうというのではありません
and go to the most distant parts
of the earth?
Well, remember,
in Acts 1:8,
使徒 1章8節で イエスは—
Jesus was speaking to people
there in Jerusalem,
エルサレムにいた人々に
話しかけていました
and you may already be living
エルサレムから見れば
わたしたちはすでに—
in one of the most distant parts
of the earth
地の最も遠い所にいることに
なるのかもしれません
when you view it
from Jerusalem’s viewpoint.
But the main thing is,
wherever we are
いずれにしても 大切なことは—
移動するにしても
自分の区域内で宣べ伝えるにしても—
—if we can reach out
and go somewhere else
or whether we can preach
within our own territory—
これらの忠実な者の手本に倣い—
if we follow the example
of these faithful ones,
音信をまだ聞いていない人を
見出すために—
we’ll be sure to try
and reach out to persons
精一杯 努力することです
それが遠い地であっても
地元であってもです
who have not had
the opportunity to hear the truth,
whether near or far.